Guide to the Gordon Alexander Craig Papers SC0467
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Writings and publications, 1934-1975; Series 4
  - Publications by G. Craig
    - Typescript of Craig's book Knowledge and Power: Historical Essays and Essays about History (Box 3, Folder 10-11)
    - Typescript of Craig's book Knowledge and Power: Historical Essays and Essays about History (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
    - Acquisition Proposal for Knowledge and Power (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Outline and clippings re: Knowledge and Power (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Observer Article and Campus Conference Speech ["Green Stamp or Structured Undergraduate Education?", April 1975] (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Reprints of articles by G. Craig (Box 4, Folder 6-9)
    - Reporter Article; Introduction to Vogt book [as well as miscellaneous articles and reviews] (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
    - Teaching Article ["College Teaching; Theory and Practice," Princeton Alumni Weekly, January 30, 1959] (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - G.A. Craig; Miscellaneous Articles, etc., [1946-1961] (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
    - Miscellaneous Publications by Craig, 1940's - 1960's (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
    - Articles [Miscellaneous] (Box 5, Folder 5-12)
  - Reviews by G. Craig
    - Germany - Bibliog Reviews (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
    - Typescript book reviews of Children's Literature in Hitler's Germany by Christa Kamenetsky and A Noble Combat: The Letters of Sheila Grant Duff and Adam von Trott zu Solz 1932-1939, edited by Klemens von Klemperer (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - The Reporter [Reviews, 1966-1968] (Box 6, Folder 4-6)
  - Reviews of G. Craig Publications
    - Reviews - War, Politics, Diplomacy (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Reviews - The Battle of Koniggratz (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Reviews in German - The Battle of Koniggratz (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Reviews - From Bismarck to Adenauer (Box 6, Folder 10-12)
  - Publications by Other Authors
    - William B. Bader, "The Zone of Twilight: Congress, The Presidency, and the Foreign Policy Powers." (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Reprints: Benda - Bendix (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Gerhard Botz (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Reprints: Boyd - Haas (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Reprints: Hinrichs - Howard (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Reprints: Hubbard - Kohn (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Kordt, Erich. Wahn und Wirklichkeit Contains annotations by Craig, (1947) (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Krausnick - Morton (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Mousnier - Rostow (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Reprints: Snell - Spranger (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Reprints: Szporluk - Woodward (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Reprints: Miscellaneous (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Items removed from Craig's books
    These files include clippings of book reviews, typescript reviews and letters.
    - Alfieri - Beitzell (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Blumenson - Brecht (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Browder - Cleugh (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Compton - Duffy (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Edwards - Finer (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Fischer - Gorlitz (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Grenzebach - Horn (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Jelavich - Kessler (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Kimmich - Kubizek (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Langer - Marshall (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Mayer - Presseisen (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Radvany - Ritter (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Rochus - Sontheimer (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Speier - Turner (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Vassiltchikov - Wollstein (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Subject files, Series 5
  - Arms Control (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bethmann-Hollweg (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Britain and the Common Market: The Politics of the Great Debate (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Britain and the Common Market: The Politics of the Great Debate (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Common Market (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chapter 25: The Crisis of Democracy in Central Europe: The Victory of National Socialism (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Diplomacy, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Diplomacy, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Diplomacy Technique, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Diplomacy Personnel (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Diplomacy: Reviews and Articles (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Diplomacy: Reviews and Articles (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Diplomatic Style (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Free University Article (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Free University Article (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Germany (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Germany: The Bulletin (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Germany - General (Reviews) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - German Literature, -1900 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Germany (Misc.) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Germany (Misc.) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - German Politics (students), 1968 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Germany - Third Reich (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Groener, Wilhelm: General (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Groener, Wilhelm: Misc. Papers (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Groener - Gleich Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Groener - Gleich Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Hitler and Army, 1933-1938 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - International Affairs 1960 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - International Relations in the 20th Century: Some New Dimensions (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - International Relations in the 20th Century: Some New Dimensions (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Middle East Crisis (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - NATO (includes correspondence from and a lecture given to the World Affairs Council) (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - NATO (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Neutrals (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - New Left Historians (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Schleicher Letters (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Soviet Policy: Style, Technique (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Summit, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Third Reich - Resistance (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Third Reich - Resistance (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Third Reich - WWII (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - US Policy (DIP) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - US Policy, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Vietnam (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Vietnam (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Vietnam (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Reviews - Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Times Literary Supplement Clippings, 1950's (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Times Literary Supplement Clippings, 1950's (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Times Literary Supplement Clippings, 1960's (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Times Literary Supplement Clippings - Germany, 1950's and 1960's (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Newspaper Clippings, 1960's (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Diaries and occasional verse [microfilm], 1935-1992; Series 6
  - Vol. 1 - 6, 1935-1946 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Vol. 7 - 10, 1946-1958 (Box 1, Reel 2)
  - Occasional Verse, 1934 - 1986 (Box 1, Reel 3)
  - Vol. 11 - 16, 1958-1966 (Box 1, Reel 4)
  - Vol. 17, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Reel 5)
  - Vol. 18 -20, 1966-1970 (Box 1, Reel 6)
  - Vol. 21 - 22, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Reel 7)
  - Vol. 23 - 25, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Reel 8)
  - Vol. 26 - 30, 1975-1978 (Box 1, Reel 9)
  - Vol. 31 - 34, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Reel 10)
  - Vol. 35 - 38, 1980-1984 (Box 1, Reel 11)
  - Vol. 39 - 41, 1984-1987 (Box 1, Reel 12)
  - Vol. 42 - 43, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Reel 13)
  - Vol. 44 - 45, 1989-1991 (Box 1, Reel 14)
  - Vol. 46, 1991 May-June 1992 (Box 1, Reel 15)
- Miscellaneous papers, Series 7
  - Es war alles gang anders: Aus der werkstatte eines palitaschen journaliste 1891-1914, 1 microfilm reel(s) (Box 1)
  - Lt. General Chaissan talk to CMC Advisory Committee on Marine Corps History, 1972 Jul 27; 1 audiotape reel(s) (Box 2)
  - Aeugen des Jahrhunderts: Gordon A. Craig, 1996; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 2)
- Restricted files, Series 8
  - Recommendation letters, tenure files, etc. (Box 1)
- Additional material, Accession ARCH-2005-169
  - Diary index cards A – R; Letter from Joachim Fest, 2003, found in old index box; Assorted certificates; Assorted photographs (including one family image); 2 Plaques; 1 audio tape (reel) Walt Rostow songs 10/31/1977; Certificate, architectural drawings, and 1 framed item pertaining to Phyllis Craig and childcare centers (Box 1)
  - Diary index cards S – Z; Diary Vol. XLIX, Oct. 1997 – Nov. 2000; Typescript volume: The Luxemburg Crisis of 1867 with Special Reference to British Policy (Craig's B. Litt. Thesis, May 1938); Typescript volume: Britain and Europe (1866-1869) A Study in the Application of Non-Intervention (Craig's dissertation, 1941); Pamphlet: Davin, D.M. Snow upon Fire: A dance to the music of Time: Anthony Powell [lecture 1976] inscribed; Hiscock, W. G. The Balliol Rhymes (Oxford: Basil Blackwell 1939) with note (Box 2)
  - Publications by Craig (Box 3)
  - Publications by Craig (Box 4)
  - Publications by Craig (Box 5)
  - Publications by Craig (Box 6)
  - Certificates and diplomas (Oxford, Princeton, University of Munich, U. S. Navy), 1935-1970 (Box 7)
  - Publications by others, with inscriptions, letters, or annotations (Box 8)
    Scope and Contents
    Carl N. Degler One Among Many: the Civil War in Comparative Perspective, 1990; 150 Jahre Orden Pour le Mérite für Wissenschaften und Künste [p. 192 is entry for Craig]; Reexamining the Soviet Experience, essays in honor of Alexander Dallin [includes letter from Bert Patenaude re his own piece]; Jurgen Barber. Bettine von Arnim (1785-1859) zu Wiepersdorf Aus Briefen [with note in German]; James J. Sheehan. Museums in the German Art World. [with note from Sheehan and annotations by Craig]; Keith Ovenden. The Greatest Sorrow [inscribed by author, with Craig’s notes on back page]; Norman M. Naimark. The Russians in Germany; a history of the Soviet Zone of Occupation, 1945-1949. [inscribed by author and with note]; Grinnerungen an Theodor Fontane 1819-1898 [with note from Konrad Meyer]; Frank E. Taplin Jr. Pages from an Oxford Diary 1937-1938 [typescript with author’s inscription]
  - Honorary degrees
- Additional material, Accession ARCH.2015-041
  - Dinkelspiel Award text written by Richard W. Lyman, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1979-2006 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photograph, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Mansfield Lecture at University of Montana, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - German Studies Association Newsletter, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Memorial Program, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters from Gordon Craig to Paul Lauren, 1985-2001 (Box 1, Folder 7)